<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to the House of Commons. Or rather to an impostor, giving answer in their names to the Londoners petition, presented to the said honourable House. Sept. 11. 1648.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E470_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205525</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864880</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117112</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117112)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E470[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to the House of Commons. Or rather to an impostor, giving answer in their names to the Londoners petition, presented to the said honourable House. Sept. 11. 1648.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1]   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Larnar, at the signe of the Black-moor, within Bishopsgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb: 4th.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th Century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117112:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPLY To the Houſe of COMMONS. Or rather to an IMPOSTOR, Giving anſwer in their Names to the <hi>LONDONERS PETITION,</hi> preſented to the ſaid Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Houſe. <hi>Sept.</hi> 11. 1648.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Larnar,</hi> at the ſigne of the Black-moor, within Biſhopſgate. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117112:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117112:2"/>
            <head>A REPLY To the Houſe of COMMONS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr being continual loſers and ſufferers by the War, is an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſufficient that we are for Peace, ſince war in it ſelf is of all humane things the moſt unwelcom, except to ſuch as blinded with the honour or commodity it brings them, and well ſecured by others from the dint and danger thereof, care not how long the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt laſts; ſince what is caſt out of the ſhip, is received into the gulph of their Ambition and Avarice.</p>
            <p>And as we have bin continual loſers and ſufferers, ſo do we not admit any hopes to make up our fortunes, or enrich our ſelves by the prolongation of the war; but propoſe (as we ever did) to get our livings by our Trades and honeſt Induſtry, and eſteem a good Peace the Crown of our earthly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
            <p>A good Peace, we ſay, for we are not ſo in love with it, as to wiſh it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any terms; in a Dungeon, in the Galleys, under the moſt inſufferable Tyrannie, there may be peace; but we would willingly, that that we are in expectation of, may be linkt with ſuch a meaſure of juſt Freedom, as ſhould make ſome recompenſe for the former war: that it ſhould likewiſe be laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which it cannot be, unleſs it be ſound: And that it may be ſo, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented our Petition to the Houſe of Commons, containing ſuch things as are not of any particular behoof to our ſelves, as ſuch or ſuch a people; but of a diffuſive and common concernment, importing an univerſal good to every honeſt man: And truly, we will not count it our boaſting, becauſe it is but our duty, in theſe ſelf-ſeeking daies eſpecially, to manifeſt a greater meaſure of ſelf-denyal. Hence do we in our publike motions (as we ought) bear both in the heart and front of them, a communicative happineſs, of which, the greateſt, the meaneſt, may partake: And though the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117112:3"/>of thoſe things we deſire, may haply diſ-reliſh the ſickly appetites of lordly and avaritious men, yet we are well aſſured, that even ſuch upon a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tl ment would quickly find, that they have bin miſtaken in their way to fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, and that it is much more eaſily attainable; and will prove leſs diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and more laſting by theſe expedients that we propoſe, than any that we have yet ſeen.</p>
            <p>For the ſcruples and objections which are raiſed againſt our Petition, in the name of the Houſe of Commons (which had bin proper enough if the pretended one at Oxford had bin now ſitting) we will reduce the weight and material circumſtances thereof, to certain heads; which if we can cleer, we queſtion not but the whole frame and fabrick of that anſwer will fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, <hi>Concerning the Kings Supremacy over the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons;</hi> We yeild that the ſtile of many of our Laws, the traditional exerciſe and belief thereof, are ſtrong on your part; and from hence, certainly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you (Royaliſts we mean) were perſwaded even to your very great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, to aſſiſt him in its vindication; and the Parliament likewiſe and their Adherents, though exceſſively abuſed and trampled upon by him, did timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and but faintly engage themſelves againſt him; ſo that at firſt the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition being ſtrong, and our underſtandings miſ-guided with the deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of above 500. yeers practiſe upon us, every King making it his buſineſs not only by power, but by Law and Parliament, to rivet the opinion of his Prerogative and Supremacy in our hearts; and having all the advantages that could be thought upon to accompliſh the ſame, as the Scholers to preach it, and mix it even with the moſt ſacred myſteries; the Lawyers to plead it; the Officers and Power of the Kingdom to ſupport it; the cuſtody of all Records, of the embezelment whereof every Age hath complained; the Licenſing of Books, whereby nothing but what made for it had publike view; and a thouſand more particular advantages that might be recited: all which conſidered, we ſay it is no wonder if at firſt both Parliament and People looked upon the King, as Recuſants upon the Pope, on whom the ſuperſtition is not more ſtrong; for we eſteemed him a thing Sacred, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable, as the Breath of our Noſtrils, the Apple of our eies, in all cauſes, and over all Perſons, next and immediate under God, Supreme Head and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, Gods Vicegerent, accountable only to him, and thereupon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the war for him. Then were we likewiſe entangled with our oaths, that ſlylie and politickly were at firſt inſinuated, and have bin ſince cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117112:3"/>and Traditionally taken, without regard to the end, or ſuſpect of the deſigne in impoſing them, which was purpoſely to enſnare the weak, and bind us to the adoration of an Image our fancies and follies have erected.</p>
            <p>But when we came to conſider the fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs of the times adminiſtring means and matter thereunto, and good men dayly writing for our Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the King on the one ſide perſiſting in his Tyranny, and endeavouring by force of Arms to eſtabliſh that power we had ſo ſmarted under before the Parliament: Hereupon (by degrees) the clouds vaniſht, the miſts of error and deception began to ſcatter, and the ſhine of Truth to appear, the eys of both Parliament and People began to open: and though at firſt, when the Parliament at Oxford was mixt with the Parliament at Weſtminſter, we profeſſed abſolutely, and without conditions, in <hi>May</hi> 1641. to defend the Kings perſon; yet afterwards in the Vow that abſurditie was omitted, and in the Covenant the condition was wiſely inſerted, <hi>in the defence of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Lawes and Liberties of England.</hi> And not only ſo, but in time the Parliament altered their Commiſſions, that to our preſent renowned General, making no mention of the defence of the Kings perſons. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in their laſt meſſage to him at Oxford, they <hi>charge him with the guilt of all the blood that has bin ſhed in this War:</hi> and tell him, <hi>that before they treat with him, he muſt make ſatisfaction to the Kingdom,</hi> calling it in their Declaration of the 11 of <hi>February</hi> 1647. <hi>a deſtructive Maxime or Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> viz. <hi>That he oweth an account of his actions to none but God alone:</hi> and voting <hi>no more addreſſes to him, but that they will of themſelves ſettle the preſent Government, ſo as may beſt ſtand with the Peace and Happineſſe of the Kingdom.</hi> So that (we hope) according to your own rule, you will not preferre thoſe unripe expreſſions that at firſt paſt from the Parliament, before thoſe that after long debates, and the wiſdom of much experience did ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely proceed from them.</p>
            <p>The Kings Supremacy was at firſt believed, becauſe not conſidered: as Turkiſh children beleeve the divinitie of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> becauſe bred up to it: but good Sir, Let it be convaſed a little. To make it good the King muſt ſhew an expreſſe grant of it; that he is above both Parliament and People: and when thats done, (which we think is impoſſible to be done,) for we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the King never durſt propoſe it in plain terms, but rather aimed at in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating it in by degrees and circumſtances, that ſo it might inſenſibly ſteal into our underſtandings, to avoid diſputes and controverſies thereupon. However we ſay, Admit the worſt, that the King can produce ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117112:4"/>made to ſome of his Predeceſſors, and ſucceſſively conveyed to him wherein he was ſo erected from the equal Flat whereon he with the reſt ſtood, (for the ſtrongeſt Royaliſts allow us at firſt equal) yet there is this further to prove, that this power was ſo alienated as not to be aſſumed; and more than that, that the preceding people in matters of Power and Liberty, can ſo bind their ſucceſſors as that it is not in their power to free themſelves, notwithſtanding never ſo apparent neceſſity thereof, or dangers that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them thereunto. This is the great point the Royaliſts fail in; They ſuppoſe, and take it for granted, and build upon it; But prove it not.</p>
            <p>Beſides, we conceive that the Kings power is a <hi>Truſt,</hi> as all power muſt needs be that is not primitive, eſpecially over others of the ſame line and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, (as we muſt needs be granted to be before the <hi>Aſſignation</hi> of ſuch a power:) Now a power in Truſt implies Conditions, mutual agreement, compact, and an inferiority in the betruſted: a liberty of revocation, of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to account; all which are implied in the relative Truſt: Now that the Kings power is a Truſt, is undenyably evident, unleſſe you will ſay that Kings are born ſuch, and had from the beginning inherent Characters of their Royalty, without any deputation from others: which is ſo abſurd, that no reaſonable man will aſſert it.</p>
            <p>Again, ſuppoſe former Parliaments made the King ſupream, not only o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver every one ſingly, but over all collectively: we ſay they either did it for his ſake or their own good and ſafety: for his ſake it is not imaginable, grant them to be of ſound minds, eſpecially if you conſider what is implyed in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy: <hi>viz.</hi> the Legiſlative power, the Sword, the diſpoſe of every mans perſon and eſtate. If then they did it conditionally, as conceiving it moſt conducing to their good and welfare, and find afterwards by thouſand ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, that it proves otherwiſe, (their end being fruſtrate,) What hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders but that they may re-aſſume and mannage their ſo much abuſed power themſelves. All this and much more we have to argue, the caſe being ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the greateſt diſadvantage of the Houſe of Commons. But let us tell you, we judge the pretended ſupremacy of Kings in this Country, never to have been fairly granted by a free and un-packt Parliament; but either forcibly uſurpt, or politickly gaind by the practice of that King-craft which every Prince hath endeavoured to make himſelf Maſter of, whoſe ultimate end is to encroach upon the Peoples Rights, and eſtabliſh its own abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſſe.</p>
            <p>We mentioned packt-Parliaments, and the truth is, much hath been
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117112:4"/>gaind that way, to the Peoples greateſt diſ-advantage, ſince all intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo gotten ſeem to have the face of conſent and allowance. But yet here Kings have been more modeſt, as dealing with ſome adverſaries at leaſt, for though by the potency of his Dependencies, by the intereſts of his Lords, Officers and Courtiers, by his conferring Barronies, and making of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Towns, he hath uſually corrupted that Fountain, which is the only orderly means of our Preſervation: yet hath there at all times in every age ſome been found, whoſe honeſt hearts have engaged them to oppoſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Kings; for which, though they have afterwards ſuffered, (for thats a ſtratagem Kings never fail'd in) yet have they thereby leſt notable. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morandums to the People of the unjuſt ſeizures of their Liberties.</p>
            <p>That the two Houſes are called <hi>His,</hi> (as you urge) is an expreſſion not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from a juſt Right, but impoſed and cuſtomarily uſed to beget a falſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of it in the hearts of weak people. So has the Militia been car'd <hi>His,</hi> the Forts and Magazins, the Ships, yea, and the very High-way: for they that would uſurpe the Right, muſt inſinuate Expreſſions agreeable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: and in this trifle (as one would think) they have been very punctual, for though there is nothing in it to convince the ſound, yet is there much to ſeduce the weak.</p>
            <p>Whereas you urge that the Houſe of Commons was inſtituted by the Kings Predeceſſors; its a foul miſtake: tis true indeed <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd what his Predeceſſors <hi>William</hi> the firſt, and ſecond, had purpoſely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, and what he then reviv'd and cal'd a <hi>Parliament,</hi> according to the Norman expreſſion, was before entituled <hi>Commune Concilium Regni,</hi> The Common Councel of the Kingdom; a name both more proper for us En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, and not as the other, importing our Norman bondage. But there is this further conſiderable in it, that as that King reviv'd it, ſo he might model and frame it beſt for his advantage, both in the Expreſſion of the Writ, and manner of the elections.</p>
            <p>That the King is the chief Officer, is not indeed agreeable to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of what he hath uſurpt upon us, for an Officer is tyed to his rules, and bounded by the Laws; But Kings have known no ſuch Bondaries, witneſs their Proclamations, and Arbitrary Impoſitions, in which their Will onely was their rule; by which, though they have done much injury to us, yet they might do more, even <hi>ad infinitum;</hi> for what have they according to your principles, to reſtrain them? Now that the exerciſe of his uſurpations ſhould be an Argument to the Parliament to eſtabliſh them, we ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117112:5"/>but rather on the contrary, a motive to their ſpeedy abolition: and therefore do we ſtile him in our Petition, <hi>the Chief Publike Officer;</hi> which is both honour enough for any one man, and by which he may do as much good as his heart can wiſh, and cannot do that hurt that hath bin uſual with Kings; and is likewiſe an appellation moſt properly ſignifying the nature of his dignity, importing a Truſt, and deputation of Power, which may be an effectual means to keep ſucceeding Kings from thoſe exorbitancies the beſt of them have through the encouragement of their Place and uſurped power lanched into.</p>
            <p>You ſay, <hi>The King is not accountable, becauſe he hath not received his Office from the People, but from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are ſtrangely miſtaken, as well in your Aſſertion, as in the Reaſon of it. In the reaſon of it firſt; for who of your wifeſt Clerks, the greateſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of Regality, allow not that Fundamental Maxime, <hi>That all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is by Conſent, ſince it is a reſtriction of that liberty for mutual and common good, that every man is born withal.</hi> Hear but one of the ableſt and greateſt Champions for the King and Church, Mr <hi>Hooker l.</hi> 1. <hi>Eccl. Pol. p.</hi> 28. <hi>The lawful power of making Laws to command whole Politick Societies of men, belongeth ſo properly unto the ſame entire Societies, that for Prince or Potenrate of what kind ſo ever upon earth, to exerciſe the ſame of himſelf, and not either by expreſs Commiſſion immediately and Perſonally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from God, or elſe by Authority derived from their conſents upon whoſe Perſons they impoſe Laws, it is no better than meer Tyrannie.</hi> And this is the common opinion of all, but ſuch as have devoted themſelves, bodies and ſouls, to the ſervice of a King: I urge not <hi>Hookers</hi> words, as if there were weight in his Authority, but to ſhew how deeply ſuperſtitious our Anſwerer is, in principles that even Royaliſts condemn; who though they derive the authority of Kings from God, yet they grant it to be convayed by a Conceſſion of the People.</p>
            <p>But let us come neerer to the point, and ſearch into times paſt, where we ſhall find, that notwithſtanding the vigilant care and induſtry of Kings to blot out and bury in oblivion whatſoever might ſeem to evidence his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeney upon the people, yet notwithſtanding, ſome glimmerings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main of that light which they thought they had wholy eclipſed. For the Conqueror, though the ſword made his entrance, yet he could not think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf faſt, til he come to an Agreement with the People, and was ſwore by them to maintain their Laws. <hi>William</hi> the ſecond, by the mediation of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117112:5"/>the Arch-Biſhop <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>frane,</hi> his own large bounty and, wide promiſes <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> the Crown. <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt ſaies <hi>Daniel,</hi> was <hi>Elected,</hi> and Crowned within four daies after his Brothers death. After the death of <hi>Henry, Stophen,</hi> Earl of <hi>Bologn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> was <hi>Elected</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and inveſted in the Crown of England: So the ſame <hi>Daniel.</hi> Now him, <hi>Henry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> though a, Frenchman born, was <hi>Admitted</hi> after the uſual Oath, to the Crown of Engl. <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt having broke his Fathers heart by an un-natural defection, and joyning with the King of France, was eſtabliſhed by the Power of the ſaid King, to whom he firſt ſwere fealty, ſo that his admiſſion was forcibly and diſorderly. King <hi>John</hi> upon condition of reſtoring the people their. Rights, and governing with moderation, was <hi>Admitted</hi> to the Crown. Thus have even our Court Hiſtorians, whether through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> advertency, or a little honeſty, I know not, but thus have they manifeſted unto us, the manner of Kings Admiſſion; to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it, by <hi>Election,</hi> and upon conditions: which yet is more notably ſpecified by <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w,</hi> in his <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, where you may find, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in being put in Parliament whether they would have this of that man, for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was four or five <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and all refuſed, till <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of Lancaſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and generally accepted. And the very Solemnity of the Coronation, is it is recorded, evidences as much; for there (after the King hath taken his Oath) the Arch-biſhop who crowns him, turns to the People, and tels them what he hath promiſed and ſworn; and then by the mouth of an Herald at Armes, asks the people, <hi>Whether they be content to ſubmit themſelves unto this man, as unto their King; or no?</hi> and ſtay is made till they give their conſents. And this you ſhall find in <hi>Stow,</hi> the moſt favourable to Kings of all Chroniclers, in his Stories of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of <hi>Henry,</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth. We might abundantly enlarge this point, but what ſpend we time to find evidences of that, the equity whereof, were there no footſteps for the practiſe extent, as it is a wonder there ſhould be, is yet in it ſelf ſo clear and manifeſt. Thoſe Kings that have bin made ſo by Odds appointment, he hath given viſible and Perſonal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands for which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> did for any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Kings: and though it, be his Ordinances that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which the neceſſity of human <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> likewiſe require, yet for the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of it, and for the Perſons Governing, it is neither appointed by any Law, Natural or Divine, (for then it ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Countries or Nations), but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of every Country <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſpective peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117112:6"/>
Being then admitted by the People, it will eaſily follow, that they are accountable to them (which cannot orderly be taken, but by the Houſe of Commons their Deputies) For their Power being not <hi>Poteſtas abſoluta,</hi> but <hi>Vicaria, &amp; Deligata,</hi> not abſolute, but delegate, and by Commiſſion given them, with Reſtrictions, Cautels, and Conditions, upon Promiſes and Oaths, how can it be that they ſhould be at liberty to do what they pleaſe to the People? and as they have, trample upon all Oaths, Laws, and Obligations, and for this be above all human queſtion or account; is not much of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Kings have ſo plentifully ſhowred upon this Nation, juſtly attributable to the licentiouſneſs of this opinion, under the ſhelter whereof they have no queſtion bin animated to the perpetration of thoſe unjuſt actions they have continually abounded in? the talk of a general Account at the day of Judgement, being a ſcare-crow their Wiſdoms contemn too much to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with. And though this Parliament have ſaid that it never entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their thoughts, to do what other Parliaments have done againſt their Kings, yet that implies not but that they may juſtly do as much, and his many cruelties, and obſtinate proſecution of the War ſince, may haply bring it into their thoughts. We ſee they allow not the maxime, of his being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to God only, but condemn it as deſtructive; by which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, that he is accountable to them; for to whom elſe can he be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able?</p>
            <p>You think much, that <hi>we charge the King with the Oppreſſions brought upon this Nation, and tell us, that the Houſe laies it upon his Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are very ſorry for it, as thinking the Principal a greater ſharer in the guilt, than the acceſſaries, the Commander, than the Agents: Alas Sir, it was as much as any mans place was worth, not to ſay or do as the King would have him: how many loſt his favour by their reluctancy: how many gained it by their officious ſervility? The reward of other mens trechery to their Countrey, was haply ſome gleanings of an Impoſition, a Place, a Fine, an Office; but had the King gone through with his work, he had bin lord of all, of every mans perſon and eſtate; and he that is the chief Agent, and greateſt Gainer in the Deſigne, we thought contracted the greateſt guilt, Beſides Sir, this man haply was employed in this buſineſs, that man in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, another in a third, and ſeveral men were inſtrumental in ſeveral evils brought upon us, but the Kings hand run through them all; and therefore according to our underſtandings, the accumulative guilt of the whole frame and model of the building belongs to him, as the prime and chiefeſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117112:6"/>
And though at firſt the Houſe of Commons (the aw of tyrannie being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them) charged the Kings Miniſters rather than himſelf; yet ſince they have placed the ſaddle right, imputing (and that moſt juſtly) our former miſeries, and the induction of the War, to the King himſelf.</p>
            <p>For our charging the Lords and Biſhops with the oppreſſions brought upon us, truly as there was a general conjunction of them both with the King in bringing in the ſame, ſo could not we diſ-joyn them in our expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and though it be an uſual fault to aſperſe an order or whole Society for the Perſonal eſcapes of a few, yet here we can diſcern no crime in it, ſince it was not a few, but almoſt all that partook in the Tytannie, and the very nature and dependency of the order it ſelf upon the Prerogative is ſuch, that it very much inclines them thereunto.</p>
            <p>For taking away ſome of the Laws eſtabliſht, (which you count hainous in us) ſo it be done in an orderly way by the Houſe of Commons, as we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, we can ſee no crime in it. It being the buſineſs and conſtant work of Parliaments, and at this time as needful as ever, ſince this Houſe hath found, that all kind of tyrannie, and thoſe Prerogatives which they have judged moſt deſtructive to the Common-wealth, have very much ſupport and countenance from the preſent Laws; and Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icadoes made up by them, againſt thoſe juſt means and expedients which neceſſity and the Peoples welfare enforce them to make uſe of.</p>
            <p>For that excellent Maxime, <hi>The ſafety of the People is above all Law:</hi> which you ſay we miſ-underſtand and miſ-apply, in uſing it to ſhake off o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and in making the People Judges of ſafety. Truly Sir, we think you have miſ-underſtood us, for we make the Houſe of Commons Judges of Safety, which they themſelves declared to be endangered, by the Kings ſetting up his Standard, before we engaged in the War. The Maxime we do but ſuggeſt, and would have them make uſe of, and we know they have frequently done it, where the Law doth not provide ſufficient remedy.</p>
            <p>You tell us, <hi>The Houſe of Commons have not denyed the Kings Negative voice,</hi> And yet Sir, they have waged a War without him; and the People, that part I mean that have aſſiſted them, have judged themſelves ſufficiently obliged by their Orders. And though hitherto they have yeilded to that cuſtomary formality, miſtaking a Ceremony for a Fundamental; a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement for a neceſſary requiſite to the eſſence of our Laws, yet do they begin to ſee through it, as appears by their Vores of no more Addreſs, and their manner of proceeding in the Treaty; where they allow not the King
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117112:7"/>that liberty which a Negative voice implies, but inſiſt upon the paſſing their Propoſitions in their own way and terms. And though we think they have even in this yeilded the King too much, conſidering the diſproportion betweem them, and his being conquered; yet by this little they give us to underſtand, that they allow not his Negative voice in that latitude he hath, claimed it.</p>
            <p>Thus by degrees you ſee all uſurpations are like to be ſeen through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which this is one of the greateſt, (moſt conducing I mean to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of Tyranny:) for by it, it is at the pleaſure of Kings, who have ever ſtudied themſelves and their own elevation, above the People; to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the paſſing of no Laws (unleſſe fore'd thereunto by the ſubjugation of Strength, as at this time) but what conduce thereunto. And though at the beginning of this Parliament he yeelded to the taking away of many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, yet they were but ſuch as he had brought upon us; and that in policy too, for the ſtopping of the Peoples mouths, and to prevent the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning of that power, by which he fore'd them in; for the maintaining where of he hath ſince ſought, and had he conquered, all on our parts had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Parliaments muſt either have no longer been, or been (as heretofore) chiefly ſerviceable to his Deſignes.</p>
            <p>'Tis to be conſidered too, that Kings have upon the yeelding to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of Oppreſſions, demanded allowance, So many Subſidies, (for example, twelve, for the taking away of Ship-mony,) or ſome other ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereof, as at this time, Conſideration is demanded for the Court of Wards, 100000. <abbr>l.</abbr>
               <hi>per annum.</hi> So that what was unduly brought upon us, and for the doing whereof, amends, ought to be made to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons damnified, ſhall yet at their very removal give us one gird more to put us in mind (were we by any injuries to be awaked) of the notorious inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of ſuch uſages.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, To this Negative Voice, I will ad only this, That what was at firſt in Kings, but as the Lord Majors ſetting to the Seal, or as Acts paſſing in Holland in the name of the Earldom of Holland, or in Venice in the name of S. <hi>Mark,</hi> (for in ſome name they muſt paſſe) has been by craft and the advantages of times crept into a liberty of Will, a Power of paſſing or not paſſing and to this the King thought to bring it in Scotland, but that they had courage to tell, him that <hi>he was bound to paſs thoſe Laws they brought,</hi> which the King then wiſely did, to avoid the Diſpute, and that England might not take example, and inſiſt upon the time here.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117112:7"/>
Where we deſire that all ſhould be alike ſubject to the Laws, you ſay, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereunto, but bring in a conſequence of your own from thence, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether forraign from our meaning: telling us that <hi>our deſire tends to have all alike, and to deſtroy all Civil Subordination.</hi> This is the uſual ſophiſtry of the times, to blaſt that which is juſt, and by all good men deſirable, by ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizing us with an opinion we as much condemn as your ſelf; wiſe men ſhould decline ſuch foul play; as if there were no difference between <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and Community; between all mens being ſubject alike to the Laws, and all mens being alike for order and degree. Our deſire imports diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Conditions, ſince it makes mention, of the ſeveral degrees we would have equally ſubjected to the Laws: As if a Lord could not be a Lord becauſe he is liable to be arreſted, or impleaded at Law. For ſhame leave ſuch ridiculous inferrences, and ſee your aptneſſe to abuſe us; which yet we have no reaſon to adviſe you to, for ſuch weakneſſes turn to our advantage.</p>
            <p>You tel us, We <hi>are not the whole People.</hi> We eaſily grant it, but all that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, though we were by many thouſands fewer then we are that approve that Petition, we hope we have that liberty which we think every ſingle man has, to preſent Petitions to the Legiſlative power, for the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, addition, or ſubſtraction of any thing our Laws abound or are defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in. And though many haply may diſſent from us, yet is it lawful for us to deſire the foreſaid Power to take what we preſent them into conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; which is not only not unlawful, but our duty, to which we are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by our gratitude and affection to our Country, of the welfare whereof every good man ought to be conſiderative.</p>
            <p>For our ſeeking Indempnity of the Houſe, of Commands for what we have done in order to their Commands, and the neceſſitie of the Service and for the good of the Common-wealth, (no further we deſire it) as ſo reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ſo neceſſary, that little importunity we hope will gain it; eſpecially when it ſhall be conſidered that the Houſe it ſelf is in equal danger of the Revival of the Enemies power as we our ſelves, and ſomewhat more, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more eminent, and partaking in the profits of this Indemonitie; which can only be made good, by the inviolable preſervation of the Houſe of Commons Supremacy, we therefore at this time were the more urgent for, fearing that by the Treaty and Act of oblivion, we ſhould not only be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred (for our faithful ſervices) guilty of the blood and miſeries of the war, (for what elſe does the Kings pardon and Act of oblivion import?) then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117112:8"/>which we had rather dy a thouſand Deaths, but alſo be made liable to the mercy (that is to the cruelty and revenge of our conquered Enemies.</p>
            <p>For the guilt you ſuppoſe we have contracted, by doing many things op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Laws in Being, we can with eaſe bear it, ſince it extends but to the Letter, not the end and intention of Laws, to preſerve which, all our Actions have bin directed; which yet neither were juſtifiable had we not had the Commands of that Power which we judge Supreme, to whom the ſafety of the Common-wealth ſo requiring, of which they and they only are the Judges,) it ſeem'd neceſſary that many things ſhould be done againſt the preſent Laws, which they then (during the violence of the Rebellion againſt them) had not time to alter: and this had they not done, they had hazarded the ſlavery or deſtruction of the Common-wealth, and the ſubju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of all Lawe, to the Will and Pleaſure of a Tyrant.</p>
            <p>You often urge us to ask pardon, as if you had already the rod over us, and were certain that this Treaty will make you our Maſters: but the beſt is, we had experience enough how pittifully apt you are to flatter your-ſelves, thinking all cock ſure and your own, when the ſucceſs hath proved quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. Your pride and preſumption indeed has undone you, which yet you will not renounce, but crow in your rags, and upon the dung-hill: ſo that a man by your writings would judge you Victors, or at leaſt in great hope to prove ſo; by ſome fancied Stratagem; ſuch as the Treaty, which yet we hope will deceive you.</p>
            <p>That we are againſt the Treaty; 'Tis becauſe thats againſt the good of the Common-wealth: and that was lately the opinion of the Houſe it ſelf. We conceive there is a neerer way to Peace, (we are ſure to a better Peace) than the Treaty can produce; What-ever-may be pretended on the other ſide, the Treaty (not-withſtanding the ſeeming large Grants) is not for Peace, but to gain abilities for War, which at this time are utterly wanting: and therefore is it that we ſay That party are the greateſt Promoters of it, that are moſt oppoſite to the Houſe of Commous. For Princes breach of Oaths, of which you ſay you are ignorant: it were an eaſy matter to ſhew you by the practice of the whole line of our Kings, and by their principles too, that no obligatious can be ſtrong enough, when they have power and opportunitie to break them. Be pleaſed to look upon the Royal Project lately printed; or but take any Hiſtory of the Engliſh Kings, and read over any Kings rain, and you will find their Oaths and Obligations to be like nets of ſiſters thred, made for neceſſity, and to divert (as they uſe to expreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117112:8"/>the preſent Torrent of Power. The Houſe cannot make him ſo free but at his time he will urge reſtraint, and 'tis the common diſcourſe of his Party, that he has no way to gain all, but by granting all, that to deceive the deceivers will be no deceit: when in the mean ſeaſon, the Prince keeps up, and the Caſtles hold out, Time is gaind, and forraign Princes are ſolicited, as in their own quarrell, to yeeld aſſiſtance. So that we cannot but ſay, That what ſeems to be the way to Peace, is indeed the means of a New war, and the laſt hopes of a conquered enemy to revive and appear again in the maintainance of their old quarrel.</p>
            <p>The true way to Peace, is the good eſtabliſhment of the Common wealth according to juſt and equal expedients, as we have preſented: Which would give ſuch good ſatisfaction to the People, (to all we mean that are not intere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the Tyranny) that no conſiderable part of them would ever be drawn to engage in a New war: and that would both keep down home-bred Inſurrections, and keep out forraign Invaders, who will never venture in, unleſſe there be a conſiderable party to receive them. And though many at preſent diſlike what we preſent in our Petition, yet upon the ſettlement thereof, they will find ſuch a real happineſs to themſelves in the Freedomes thereof, and ſo little particular or private advantage to us or any elſe, that they will ſoon, with us, bleſſe God for the ſame, and blame themſelves for having been both their own enemies and the Common-wealths.</p>
            <p>And thus I have run through the moſt material ſcruples of our Anſwerer, for the reſt, another time ſhall ſerve, becauſe we would not weary the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with too large a Treatiſe. We ſhall ſay no more at this time, but pray to God to bleſs us, and all men elſe, in our motions for common good, and blaſt us and others, when ever we or they ſhall wittingly proſecute ought that may tend to the dammage of our Country.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
